Guide to the Archibald MacLeish Collection Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Archibald MacLeish Collection Addition
1801-1995
YCAL MSS 269
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
23.10
(48 boxes) + 1 bust
The Archibald MacLeish Collection Addition consists of material related to the life and career of the American poet Archibald MacLeish received by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library after the processing of the Archibald MacLeish Collection acquired in 1976. The Addition consists of correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, personal papers, and sound recordings documenting MacLeish and his family between 1801 and 1995.
MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William MacLeish, 1996 and 2006. Other material came to the library in small quantities from various sources as indicated on individual folders.
Associated Materials
Archibald MacLeish Collection YCAL MSS 38.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Correspondence between Archibald MacLeish and Ishbel MacLeish (box 17) and Archibald MacLeish and Ada MacLeish (boxes 1- 14) in Series IV are restricted until 21 November 2045. For further information, consult the curator.
Restricted Fragile Papers, housed in boxes 43-46 and 48-50, may be consulted only with the permission of the appropriate curator. Access copies of sound recordings for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Archibald MacLeish (1892-1982)
A biographical sketch of Archibald MacLeish can be found in the finding aid for the Archibald MacLeish Collection YCAL MSS 38.
Scope and Contents
The Archibald MacLeish Collection Addition consists of material related to the life and career of the American poet Archibald MacLeish received by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library after the processing of the Archibald MacLeish Collection acquired in 1976. The Addition contains correspondence, writings, personal papers, and sound recordings documenting Archibald and Ada MacLeish's personal life, family history, and careers. It also contains correspondence and personal papers documenting the personal and professional life of MacLeish's parents, Andrew MacLeish and Martha Hillard MacLeish, including letters from Archibald and Ada MacLeish as well as from Archibald's siblings Bruce, Ishbel, Kenneth, and Norman. Correspondence, writings, and objects documenting MacLeish's maternal ancestors, the Hillards, and correspondence to William MacLeish (Archibald and Ada MacLeish's son) are also included.
Arrangement
The Archibald MacLeish Collection Addition is organized into seven series: Archibald and Ada MacLeish Correspondence; Writings; Personal Papers; MacLeish Family Papers; Hillard Family Papers; William MacLeish Correspondence; and Sound Recordings.
American drama -- 20th Century; American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Drama -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- 20th Century; Playwriting -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Authors; Dramatists; Poets; Hemingway, Ernest, 1899-1961; MacLeish, Ada; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; MacLeish, Kenneth, 1894-1918; MacLeish, William H., 1928-; Murphy, Gerald, 1888-1964; Origo, Iris, 1902-1988; Hellard family; MacLeish family
- Archibald and Ada MacLeish Correspondence, 1910 - 1982, undated; Series I; 7.09; (19 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged into three subseries: Letters between Ada and Archibald MacLeish, General Correspondence, and Condolence Letters. Some correspondents are present in both General Correspondence and Condolence Letters.
  Scope and Contents
  The correspondence documents the MacLeishs' relationship with each other as well as their relationships with family and friends. To a smaller extent the correspondence also evidences Archibald MacLeish's career.
  - Letters between Ada and Archibald MacLeish
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted until 2045 November 21
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - General A-Z, 1915-1982 (Box 15, Folder 140-144)
    - Adato, Perry Miller, 1979 May 8 (Box 15, Folder 145)
      Includes proposal for a film on Carl Sandburg and biography of Adato
    - Barnes, Joseph, 1950 (Box 15, Folder 146)
    - Bundy, Katherine, 1924-1971, undated (Box 15, Folder 147-150)
    - Bundy, McGeorge, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 151)
      Includes copy of Bundy's speech at the International Publishers Association Congress
    - Ciardi, John, 1978 (Box 15, Folder 152)
    - Hemingway, Ernest, undated (Box 15, Folder 153-154)
      Photocopies of letters dating from 1924 to 1958 and undated
    - Hitchcock, William and Emily Boyle, 1913 (Box 16, Folder 155-160)
      Includes letter from Emily Hitchcock to Kathryn Bell
    - Independent Citizens' Committee of the Arts, Sciences and Professions, 1944-1946 (Box 16, Folder 161)
    - MacLeish, Bruce, 1919-1952 (Box 16, Folder 162)
    - MacLeish, Ishbel, 1917-1980, undated (Box 17, Folder 163-172)
    - MacLeish, Kenneth, 1917, undated (Box 18, Folder 173)
    - MacLeish, Kenneth (Jr.), undated (Box 18, Folder 174)
    - MacLeish, Mary, undated (Box 18, Folder 175)
    - MacLeish, Norman, 1940-1971 (Box 18, Folder 176-177)
    - MacLeish, William, 1980, undated (Box 18, Folder 178)
    - Mort, Judith, 1981 (Box 18, Folder 179)
      Relates to Hillard family
    - Murphy, Gerald, undated (Box 18, Folder 180-181)
      Photocopies of letters from 1935 to 1964 (including 1929 letter from Dorothy Parker to Robert Benchley)
    - Origo, Iris, 1958-1978, undated (Box 18, Folder 182-184)
    - Reagan, Ronald, 1982 (Box 18, Folder 185)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 186)
    - Thatcher, Isabel, 1978 (Box 18, Folder 187)
    - U.S. War Department, 1918 (Box 18, Folder 188)
    - White, Constance, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 189)
    - ----, Ray., 1968 (Box 18, Folder 190)
  - Condolence Letters
    - General A-Z, 1982 (Box 19, Folder 191-203)
- Writings, 1915-1983; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Writings are arranged into six subseries: Articles, Poetry, Playscripts, Speeches, Reviews, and Writings of Others. MacLeish's writings are arranged alphabetically by title and Writings of Others is arranged alphabetically by author (when known).
  - Articles
    - "Lift the Ban", photocopy of printed version, The Nation 167.2, 1948 July 10 (Box 20, Folder 204)
    - "Riders on the Earth Together, Brothers in Eternal Cold", printed excerpt from The New York Times, 1968 December 25 (Box 20, Folder 205)
    - "What She Was Herself", photocopy of printed version, The New York Times, 1972 June (Box 20, Folder 206)
    - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 20, Folder 207)
  - Poetry
    - "Alien", printed version, 1931 (Box 20, Folder 208)
      Song by Richard E. Myers dedicated to Ada MacLeish with lyrics by Archibald MacLeish
    - "Conquistador"
      - Page proofs, corrected, 1932 (Box 20, Folder 209)
      - Folio of original woodcut prints, 1932
        15.75 x 12
    - "Grief", printed version, 1915 April (Box 20, Folder 210)
      The Yale Review (New Haven, Connecticut: Yale Publishing Association)
    - "Poems", printed versions, 1954 July (Box 20, Folder 211)
      Poems printed in The Atlantic Monthly include: "Poet", "The Wood Dove at Sandy Spring", "And Out of Weakness Song"
    - Tower of Ivory, drafts, holograph, corrected, circa 1917
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Notebooks
    - "Voyage to the Moon", printed version from New York Times, 1969 July 21 (Box 20)
  - Playscripts
    - "J.B.", typed playscript, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 212)
      John Tydeman's BBC radio adaptation
  - Speeches
    - "Conversation with the Moon", printed version, 1977 May 17 (Box 20, Folder 213)
      Delivered at the fourteenth Cosmos Club Award, Washington, D.C.
    - "The Crisis of the Diminished Man", typescript, Undated (Box 20, Folder 214)
      Delivered at University of California, Berkeley
    - "Frost and Stone", printed version, Amherst Alumni News: The Presidential Convocation and Ground Breaking for the Robert Frost Library, 1963 Fall (Box 20, Folder 215)
    - National Medal for Literature award, typed excerpts, 1978 April 6 (Box 20, Folder 216)
      Delivered at the New York Public Library
    - "Poetry and Journalism", printed version, 1958 October 12 (Box 20, Folder 217)
      Delivered at the University of Minnesota, Minneapolis
    - "The Poet and the Press", printed version, 1959 March (Box 20, Folder 218)
      Reprinting in The Atlantic of MacLeish's speech "Poetry and Journalism"
    - Pulitzer Prize awards, typescript, 1966 May 10 (Box 20, Folder 219)
    - "Speech to be Delivered Before the Renaissance Society of Chicago", typescript, Undated (Box 20, Folder 220)
    - Untitled, holograph, 1979 April (Box 20, Folder 221)
      Speech on MacLeish's mother Martha Hillard MacLeish
    - "The Viewpoint of Modern Art", holograph, 1946 March (Box 20, Folder 222)
      Delivered to the Arts Club in St. Augustine, Florida
    - "Yeats and the Belief in Life", printed version, 1957 January 17 (Box 20, Folder 223)
      Delivered at the University of New Hampshire
  - Reviews of MacLeish's Work
    - Reviews, 1919-1986 (Box 20, Folder 224)
    - Scrapbook of reviews, 1976-1977, undated (Box 20)
  - Writings of Others
    - Becker, Stephen, "On Being a Patient", The Atlantic Monthly, Undated (Box 20, Folder 225)
    - Benco, Nancy, "Archibald MacLeish: The Poet Librarian", The Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, 33.3, 1976 July (Box 20, Folder 226)
    - Cowley, Robert, "American Was Promises: An Interview with Archibald MacLeish", American Heritage 33.5, 1982 August/September (Box 20, Folder 227)
    - Cunningham, Phyllis Fenn, "My Aunt and Godmother: Miss Mary Robbins Hillard, Founder and First Principal of Westover School", 1983 (Box 20, Folder 228)
    - MacLeish, Rod, "Columbus Day Broadcast" typescript for WVDA ABC Radio in Boston, Undated (Box 20, Folder 229)
    - Unidentified, "Introduction to Elfin Dance", Undated (Box 20, Folder 230)
- Personal Papers, 1892-1982, undated; Series III; 1.67; (5 boxes)
  Personal Papers are organized into three subseries: Diaries Scrapbooks, and Photographs, Other Papers, and Objects.
  - Diaries, Scrapbooks, and Photographs
    - "Westover Year-Book", 1911 (Box 21, Folder 231)
    - "School in Paris 1913-1914" (Box 21, Folder 232-233)
      Album contains black and white photographs of Ada MacLeish's studies in France and travels in Europe and North Africa
    - Scrapbook containing photographs of Ada and Archibald MacLeish, 1892 - circa 1980s (Box 21)
    - Scrapbook of Ada and Archibald MacLeish's trip to Japan, 1937 (Box 22, Folder 234-241)
      Contains souvenirs and black and white photographs of the MacLeishs' travels in Japan for Archibald MacLeish's work with Fortune Magazine
    - Ada MacLeish's diary of Japan trip, 1937 (Box 23, Folder 242-243)
    - Notebooks, circa 1917 (Box 23, Folder 244-245)
      Contains notes on medicine and expenses as well as drafts of poetry for Tower of Ivory
    - Photographs of MacLeish family and friends, 1892-1982, undated (Box 23, Folder 246-248)
    - Photographs of MacLeish family and friends, 1892-1982, undated (Box 24, Folder 249-258)
      Includes portrait of Ada MacLeish by Man Ray
    - Scrapbooks of family home Craigie Lea, 1895, undated (Box 24)
  - Other Papers
    - Letters of recommendation for military service, 1917 (Box 25, Folder 259)
      Includes black and white photograph of MacLeish
    - Material relating to honorary degrees from University of Dubuque (Iowa) and University of Massachusetts, 1969 and 1977 (Box 25, Folder 260)
    - Certificates, 1917-1918, undated (Box 25, Folder 261)
    - Concert Programs and Reviews documenting Ada MacLeish's career, circa 1911-1954 (Box 25, Folder 262-263)
    - Concert Posters for Ada MacLeish's performance while living in France, 1927 (Box 25)
    - Playbill for Scratch, 1971 (Box 25, Folder 264)
    - Clippings and ephemera, 1907-1976 (Box 25, Folder 265-268)
    - Memorials for Archibald MacLeish, 1982 (Box 25, Folder 269-270)
    - Papers and photographs relating to Kenneth MacLeish, 1919 (Box 25, Folder 271-274a)
      Includes publication Kenneth: A Collection of Letters
  - Objects
    - Bronze bust of Archibald MacLeish by Milton Hebald, undated; 19.25 x 8 x 10.25 inches (Box 25)
- MacLeish Family Papers, 1888-1968; Series IV; 1.67; (5 boxes)
  The MacLeish Family Papers are organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Personal Papers.
  The MacLeish Family Papers contain correspondence, writings, and personal papers documenting the personal and professional life of Andrew MacLeish and Martha Hillard MacLeish (Archibald MacLeish's parents).
  - Correspondence
    - General A-Z, 1920-1927 (Box 26, Folder 275-284)
    - Hendryx, Anna Harrison, 1910-1911, undated (Box 26, Folder 285)
    - Hillard, Elias Brewster, 1890, 1895 (Box 26, Folder 286)
    - MacLeish, Ada, 1913-1968, undated (Box 27, Folder 287-305)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, transcriptions, undated (Box 27, Folder 306-307)
      Letters transcribed originally written in 1918
    - MacLeish, Ishbel, 1919 (Box 28, Folder 308)
    - MacLeish, Kenneth, 1918 (Box 28, Folder 309)
    - MacLeish, Kenneth, transcriptions, undated (Box 28, Folder 310-312)
      Letters transcribed originally written between 1917 and 1918
    - MacLeish, Norman, 1918-1921 (Box 29, Folder 313-323)
    - MacLeish, Norman, transcriptions, undated (Box 29, Folder 324-329)
      Includes typed and handwritten transcriptions of letters originally written between 1918 and 1920
    - ---, Porter., 1918 (Box 29, Folder 330)
  - Writings
    - Essays by Martha Hillard MacLeish, undated (Box 30, Folder 331-337)
  - Other Papers
    - Certificates and clippings relating to Martha Hillard MacLeish, 1888-1947 (Box 30, Folder 338)
    - Will for Andrew MacLeish, 1923 (Box 30, Folder 339)
    - Journal of Norman MacLeish, 1937 (Box 30, Folder 340)
- Hillard Family Papers, 1801-1884, undated; Series V; 1.88; (5 boxes)
  The Hillard Family Papers are arranged into two subseries: Correspondence and Personal Papers.
  The Hillard Family Papers contain correspondence and personal papers documenting the lives of Archibald MacLeish's maternal ancestors.
  - Correspondence
    - Barrett, Sara Ann Hillard, 1816-1884, undated (Box 31, Folder 341-348)
    - Hammond, Eliza Hillard, 1877, undate (Box 31, Folder 349)
    - Hillard, Eliza Williams Kellogg, 1825-1868 (Box 32, Folder 350-361)
    - Hillard, Eliza Williams Kellogg, 1871-1898, undated (Box 33, Folder 362-373)
    - Hillard, Sally Pride, 1801-1826, undated (Box 34, Folder 374-381)
    - Vance, Annie Kellogg Hammond, 1903, undated (Box 34, Folder 382)
  - Other Papers
    - Unattributed writing fragments, undated (Box 35, Folder 383-384)
    - Partage de Héritages de feu Jean Helier Dumaresq, 1815 May 13 (Box 35, Folder 385)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 35, Folder 386)
      Three black and white photographs (one of Mary Ann Hillard and two of unidentified people)
    - Financial records, circa 1850 - 1876, undated (Box 35, Folder 387-389)
    - Hazeltine, Miron. Beadle's Dime Chess Instructor, circa 1840 (Box 35, Folder 390)
    - Eraser, seal stamp, and ink well, undated (Box 35, Folder 391-393)
- William MacLeish Correspondence, Series VI; 0.21; (1 box)
  - General A-Z, 1979-1995 (Box 36, Folder 394)
  - Donaldson, Gordon, 1982 (Box 36, Folder 395)
    Includes copy of Archibald MacLeish's death certificate
  - MacLeish, Ada, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 396)
    Contains inscribed chapter from William MacLeish's memoir Uphill With Archie
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1981-1984, undated (Box 36, Folder 397)
    Includes copy of corrected typescript of Archibald MacLeish's poem "Whistler in the Dark"
  - McAdoo, Dick, 1983-1984 (Box 36, Folder 398)
    Includes typescript excerpts from Archibald MacLeish's journal from a trip to Persia in 1926 as well as a typescript copy of Archibald MacLeish's book Poems
- Sound Recordings, Series VII; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Sound Recordings are organized into the following three subseries: Interviews, Plays, and Poetry.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Reference copies of sound recordings are filed in the folders.
  Boxes 43-46 and 48-50 contain audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Interviews
    Boxes 43-45 and 48-50 contain audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Interview with Studs Turkel, W.F.M.T., 1960 November 25; 1 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091243577)
    - "MacLeish and His Two Worlds", Canadian Broadcasting Corporation
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan circa 1971, Master Tape I (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 48 (Record album storage), Item barcode 39002099364805)
        Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan circa 1971, Master Tape 2 (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 48 (Record album storage), Item barcode 39002099364813)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, MacLeish I, undated; 1 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091243585)
        Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult access services for further information.
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, MacLeish 2, undated; 1 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091243593)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, MacLeish Dub 1A, undated; 1 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091243601)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, MacLeish Dub 1B, undated; 1 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091243619)
      - MacLeish Music, undated; 1 (Box 43, Item barcode 39002091243627)
        Contents included with this audiotape reel are listed below.
        William Schuman, New England Triptych - "When Jesus Wept"
        Charles Griffes, "Poem for Flute"
        Peter Mennin, "Canto"
        Randall Thompson, "Largo"
        Ron Nelson, "For Katherine in april"
        Martin Mailman, "Autumn Landscape"
        "Le Boeuf Surle Toit Darius Milhaui"
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, Tuesday Night, MacLeish Dub 1, undated; 1 (Box 44, Item barcode 39002091243635)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, Tuesday Night, MacLeish Dub 2, undated; 1 (Box 44, Item barcode 39002091243643)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, Tuesday Night rebroadcast accompanied by selections of American music #1 (1 of 4 audiotape reels), undated; 1 (Box 48 (Record album storage), Item barcode 39002099364821)
      - Introduction by Malcolm Cowley to Patrick Hynan interview, Sveriges Radio, Swedish Broadcasting Corporation, circa 1971; 1 (Box 44, Item barcode 39002091243650)
        Produced by Varcoe de Radwan
      - Cowley, excerpts and fragments from introduction to Archibald MacLeish and other commentary, circa 1971; 1 (Box 44, Item barcode 39002091243668)
      - Excerpts and fragments from introduction to Archibald MacLeish and other commentary (audiotape reel), circa 1971; 1 (Box 50 (Record album storage), Item barcode 39002099364862)
      - Archibald MacLeish teasers, 2nd take, circa 1971; 1 (Box 44, Item barcode 39002091243676)
      - "The Teacher and the Lively Arts: Archibald MacLeish", The Education Council for School Research and Development, copy 1, 1967 November 1; 1 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091243940)
        3.75 ips
      - Unidentified interview, undated
        See: "Bubble of Blue Air", read by President Richard Nixon during inaugural address / Patrina
      - Music selections, undated; 1 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091243924)
      - Music selections for MacLeish program, undated; 1 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091243932)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, Tuesday Night rebroadcast accompanied by selections of American music, Tape 1 (2 of 4 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 49 (Record album storage), Item barcode 39002099364839)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, Tuesday Night rebroadcast accompanied by selections of American music, Tape 3 (3 of 4 audiotape reels), undated; 1 (Box 49 (Record album storage), Item barcode 39002099364847)
      - Interview with Patrick Hynan, Tuesday Night rebroadcast accompanied by selections of American music #4 (4 of 4 audiotape reels), undated; 1 (Box 49 (Record album storage), Item barcode 39002099364854)
  - Plays
    - "The Fall of the City"
      - Voice of America, United States Information Agency, undated; 1 (Box 45, Item barcode 39002091243957)
        Recording from 1937 April 11 performed by Orson Welles, House Jameson, and Burgess Meredith,Columbia Broadcasting System; 7.5 ips
      - University of Detroit Broadcasting Guild, 1962; 1 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002091243965)
        Includes interview with House Jameson (who also performs in production)
      - W.F.M.T., 1968 September 9; 1 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002091243973)
        Read by Studs Turkel, mono dub at 7.5 ips, full track, 30 minutes each
      - The Theatre of Freedom, Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, 1971 September 21; 1 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002091243981)
      - The Theatre of Freedom, Canadian Broadcasting Corporation, 1971 September 21; 1 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002091243999)
      - J.B. Music-Opening-Music / "Curse God and Die" / "Mr. Zuss' Summation", undated; 1 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002091244005)
  - Poetry
    - "Bubble of Blue Air", read by President Richard Nixon during inaugural address / Patrina, undated; 1 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002091244013)
    - "You, Andrew Marvell", read by Archibald MacLeish, undated; 1 (Box 46, Item barcode 39002091244021)
- Oversize, 5.69; (4 boxes)
  - "Voyage to the Moon", printed version from New York Times (Series IV), 1969 July 21 (Box 39, Folder 429)
  - Reviews (Series IV), 1919-1986 (Box 39, Folder 430)
  - Scrapbook of reviews (Series IV), 1976-1977, undated (Box 40, Folder 431)
  - Scrapbook containing photographs of Ada and Archibald MacLeish (Series IV), 1892 - circa 1980s (Box 40, Folder 432)
  - Photographs of MacLeish family and friends (Series IV), 1895-1982, undated (Box 41, Folder 433-436)
  - Scrapbooks of family home Craigie Lea, 1895, undated (Box 41, Folder 437-438)
  - Photographs of MacLeish family and friends (Series IV), 1895-1982, undated (Box 42, Folder 439-441)
  - Concert Posters (Series IV), 1927 (Box 42, Folder 442)
  - Clippings relating to family and friends (Series IV), 1926-1943 (Box 42, Folder 443)
  - Bronze bust of Archibald MacLeish by Milton Hebald (Series IV), undated (Box Art, Folder 444)
  - "Conquistador" folio of original woodcut prints (Series II), 1932 (Box 47, Folder 474-481)